Did you start live stream as well?
OK, everything's good.
Thank you.
OK, welcome back.
Good afternoon.
So lecture 22, I hope you had a nice holiday yesterday.
Today is actually also a holiday for children in school.
Fortunately or unfortunately, it's not a holiday for us.
My son was actually was confused.
That's why I'm working today.
So let's see.
I hope the lecture is exciting today.
OK, so today we're going to continue from the point that we left off last week regarding memory
hierarchy.
And then we're going to get to the caches and how we organise and design cache architectures.
So these are some reading for this lecture and probably also some for next week because we are not
going to cover everything in this lecture today, OK.
So remember record that we discussed about memory which is critical for computing and it's critical
because of performance, energy, robustness, cost, form factor, sustainability and and so on and so
forth.
We covered some fundamentals on memory last week.
We remember about this idealised memory that essentially we want 0 access time, infinite capacity, 0
cost, infinite bandwidth and 0 energy.
And essentially it's really it's not possible to really achieve all of them together.
It's not even possible to achieve one of them also any of them because 0 is very absolute number and
infinite is also very high.
And then essentially we also discuss about memory arrays.
We started with this review slide that we've seen also in the beginning of the lectures.
I guess in lecture three of two or three that essentially flip flops are really fast, but they are
expensive.
We also have a static RAM which they are also relatively fast, but they are less expensive compared
to flip flops and DRAM and other storage media like flash memory, hard disk, antique.
So this slide is actually important because as we described today, we want, we're going to make
hierarchy of all these different memory technologies and also different sizes of the memory.
So and essentially as we go down, things are getting slower and also getting less costly and and
that's actually going to shape the trade off that we're going to do in this hierarchy.
OK.
And also this area organizational memory that essentially most of memories are actually considered
like this that you have you may get array for a bank and you provide address and you basically
fetch data or you write the data that on the ad location that the address is pointing to.
Yeah.
And essentially we discuss about, you know, how we can make larger memories that we essentially we
need to, you know, make a hierarchy in that memory.
And therefore that we discuss, you know, as an example, in DRAM we have channels, rank bank
subarrays and Mats, which you've seen that in the previous lecture.
And we discussed about this top down and bottom up design of the DRAM architecture, DRAM subsystem
organization in detail, OK.
And we were also discussing about memory technology like DRAM, which you've seen also that there is
a capacitor and also access transistor.
And we know that this capacitor leaks through the RC pass, which is resistor capacitor pass because
things are not ideal here.
And because of that DRAM cell loses DRAM cell loses charge over time.
And we do need to refresh DRAM.
Also we discussed about the static RAM SRAM, which essentially we store data in a cross couple, 2
cross couple inverters.
And you know that for each of these inverter we need 2 transistors.
So in overall we have 4 transistor, but at the same time we also need to add other transistors in
order to be able to write and what we want to store in this SRA, OK, so we were around this part
that we basically stop.
So, yeah, so memory bank organization, regardless of the memory technology is more or less something
like that.
So essentially you have a, you provide address and there is address register and this address is
going to be fed to the row decoder in order to find which row you want to access.
And part of the address which is usually low significant bit or sorry least significant bits are
going to fit to this multiplexer in order to select the column or basically several bytes or
several bits that you are reading.
Out so, so in the read access sequence, first you need to decode the row address and drive forward
lines.
And then you selected bit drives bit lines.
So we read entire row and then we need to amplify the row data and decode the column address using
this least significant bits to send to the output.
And then we need to pre charge the bit lines for the next accesses essentially.
So that's a overview overall design of the memory bank.
Also in SRAM, we have the similar structure.
I'm not going into detail of that, but essentially in ridiculous, you also need to provide the
address first and you drive row enable and selected with sales drive bit lines same as before.
And essentially we have the sensing differential sensing and column select.
So the sensing, differential sensing in this RAM is a little bit different from DRAM.
We're not going into detail of how we design it, but things are very much similar and we need to pre
charge also all bit lines again.
So in also in SRM access, access latency dominated by Step 2 and three like how fast you can drive
the word line and how fast you can essentially your bit lines are going to be driven with the data
and essentially.
So these two, the latency of Step 2 is dependent on the on the number of columns that you have,
because the more columns, the the word line is going to be longer and you need to basically wait
longer until the IT has enough charge.
And the the bit line.
Also, the latency of the bit line for the Step 3 is determined by the essentially professional to to
2 to the power N, which is the number of rows.
The more rows you have, the longer bit line you're going to have.
And then that's going to essentially specify the latency of your strap.
For Dean, I'm also we've seen it, so I'm not going to detail of that.
But yeah, in DRAM essentially we know that bit cell loses charge when read and bit cell loses charge
over time.
So essentially we need, we do need to refresh DRAM.
We don't need to refresh SRAM, but in DRAM we do need to do refreshing.
And also when we read from DRAM, read is actually destructive.
So you need to wait after sensing to restore the charge in the in your capacitor in DRAM.
But for SRAM, for example, we don't need to do that as so rate sequence in DRAM is step one to three
similar as a SCRAM.
But then we have this flip flopping sense amplifier to amplify and regenerates the bit line.
And then also we need to pre charge and we know about destructive reads and charge loss over time
and that we need to do refresh.
But these are more or less kind of review from you.
Any questions?
OK.
So now let's quickly compare DRAM and SRAM because in so the point here is that we want to show that
these memory technologies they are not none of them are perfect in all aspects.
So there are Reds and greens and so we have trade off here.
So in DRAM actually we have compared to SRAM, we have a slower access because of the capacitor and
that capacitor is actually small and then you need to spend some time for chart trading and then
also sensing that.
So sensing that the small charge in that capacitor is not really easy and that would actually cause
one of the reason that we have longer latency in DRAM accesses.
But because of that the small transistor actually DRAM is much have much higher density.
So it's one T1C cell and lower costs relatively to a STRAM.
But DRAM requires refresh and that refresh actually comes at the price of power, performance and
some circuitry because you need to consume power consumption for doing refreshing.
So if your system is actually either for a long time, even that idle.
Also your DRAM needs to get refreshed every 10s of milliseconds and that would consume power.
And while you are the 1 to access your DRAM, sometimes your DRAM cannot be accessed or at least some
part of your DRAM, some banks they cannot be accessed because you are doing refresh in that part of
your DRAM.
So that would also comes at their performance penalty.
And also you need to provide some circuitry for doing the refresh which also you know has some
overheads.
And another issue with DRAM is that unfortunately manufacturing requires putting capacity and logic
together.
So essentially the manufacturing process of DRAM and CMOS are not very much similar and that's why
actually DRAM is not integrated much in the processor chip.
So if you really want to do that, then your processor chip is going to be much, very much
inefficient because of.
A lot of reason that I don't want to go into detail of that.
So that's why these two are separated.
And so when you look at the processor chip, you actually don't see DRAM in your processor chip.
You do see SRAM.
Actually you do see a lot of SRAM because of caches that we're going to see a lot.
But DRAM are not there because of the manufacturing process difference in manufacturing difference
in manufacturing process.
So SRAM compared to DRAM is much faster and we don't have capacitor which is good.
So when you don't have capacitor then you can actually design it with a similar integration
technology that you have for processor chip but has lower density because of the 60 cent and higher
cost.
SRAM doesn't need to refresh which is also good and and also manufacturing compatible with logic
process.
So these are the good things about the SRAM.
But for example, if you want to design the whole system with the strand, then we're going to have
problem with the density of a strand.
Then you're going to have a, you know, the motherboard, which might be, you know, as big as this
table, for example.
OK, this is just an assigned that these are not the only tech memory technology that we have DRAM
and strand.
There are also a lot of other technologies which you can think of as a emerging memory technologies
that they are not that mature, but they are very interesting to look into it because they also have
some goods and bads.
And then essentially designing the system.
By knowing some other memory technologies, you might be able to get a much more balanced system
design.
So this is the topic that actually our group have worked a lot on that Face change memory is one
example of that.
In face change memory you have a material like for example Charcoganite glass which this glass
actually has two states.
One state is amorphous which has low optical reflexivity and high electrical resistivity and another
phase of that material which is crystalline which has high optical reflexivity and low electrical
resistivity.
So with that since you have two different state of that material, you can essentially you can use
that to store.
So once for example as a, if you think about as a like optical difference reflex reflexivity with
the optical.
So you just shine the light on your material and see if if the material has like high reflexivity,
you realise that OK, my material is in crystalline situation.
And then you can encode that situation as one or zero, whatever you want.
So you can actually understand how they reflex the light after shining.
And based on the the fact you can see if you're in amorphous state or crystalline state, you can
also derive with some current, you know the material.
And then depending on the resistance that you're observing from the material, you can you can
understand that you're in amorphous state or crystalline state.
And these two actually has been used, both of them.
If you know about CD rewritable CDs, have you, do you have you ever used relatable CDs?
Yeah, I use a lot.
So these are actually one of the interesting technology in CD rewritable CDs is that that
essentially use exactly the same material there and you decide based on this amorphous or
crystalline.
But later on people work a lot to see how they can design some, let's say, electrical electronic
circuit in order to understand the resistance of the material.
And with that you can actually have a sensing circuitry which you can do it electrically.
IBM is one of the companies that also work a lot on that and they actually publish one of the
earliest paper in that line.
And with that, actually, once you can have it as electrics electronic circuit, then you can actually
use them as a memory, which is much faster.
So this operation of shining light and check the reflexive of that is actually very small slow.
And that's why rewritable C DS are very slow.
But using this electrical circuits actually you can make it much faster.
And after that point, actually, we, we, we observed this shift in computer architecture that people
started using this PCM as a, as a main memory or as a combination to the main memory.
So our group also work a lot in this paper.
Actually, we try to replace the whole DRAM with PCMPCM.
There are also other options of that, that you can basically use DRAM and PCM together as a hybrid
memory.
But basically I'm, I'm not going to go into detail of that.
If you're interested, you can check these papers.
But essentially when if you move.
I mean use PCM completely as your main memory, then you have problems because of the longer latency
and you need to design some techniques in order to provide, I mean mitigate the overhead of longer
latency and longer energy.
But at the same time PCM is much denser which provides you much higher density.
So these are some papers about using pure PCM main memory and also hybrid PCM DRAM which you can
check if you're interested.
And this is one of the paper that I was talking about.
OK, Intel also has used it and they designed this non volatile memory based on three DX point
technology which is very much similar to PCM and these obtain persistent memory.
They have proposed which you can actually you could have bought these themes and put in your
computer and use the this large memory.
So you can see that the size of it is actually 128 GB, which is relatively actually very high
capacity compared to DRAM teams.
And they also have another branch of it which you essentially use obtain for for SSDs.
So normally in a solid-state drive, you use flash memory, but you can also use obtain 3DX point as
as a for your storage media.
That would also provide fast higher performance.
Yeah, unfortunately Intel has stopped actually this line for persistent memory for some business
reasons, not, I'm not saying that much really scientific reasons, but from the business point of
view, they really couldn't I guess integrate nicely in their fabrication lab to reduce the cost.
So still fabricating such memories is actually costly and we cannot amortize overhead with.
OK, so now let's quickly also compare DRAM with phase change memory so or PCM.
So compared DRAM compared to PCM is faster, but actually much lower density.
So PCM is actually slower because so when you when you want to change the and that the phase of the
material you need to do heating and cooling essentially.
So by electrical circuits, you actually provide some current to your material and that current needs
to follow some pulse.
And with that you, for example, you heat the material and then you cool it down quickly or you heat
it in a longer time.
So based on that you can actually set different, you know, the phase of the material and that is
actually costly in terms of latency and also energy.
However, PCM has much higher density and this actually density is coming from 2 main reasons.
1 is that first of all you can scale PCM much better.
So DRAM is actually considered as a charge memory which you you store charge in capacitor.
And as you downscale DRAM at that capacity is getting smaller and smaller and smaller.
And that's essentially sensing that a small charge is becoming much more harder and and also causing
a lot of read disturbance issues that we are observing today.
However, for PCM actually people have showed that we can actually scale it much better with less
issues.
So PCM is potentially can provide the higher density because of the scalability.
And also in PCM you can store multiple bits in one set.
So with discuss about the resistive value and you can actually partition your resistive, let's say
window in only two steps.
And then you can encode it into only one bit like 0 or 1:00.
But you can also do it much, let's say with higher accuracy and you divide or you basically chop
the, you know, the distribution of resistance in four steps.
And with that you can essentially send 2 bits or you can do it 8 location and then you sense 3 bits.
And that's another angle that caused PCM have higher density compared to DRAM.
For DRAM also it's, it's not very easy as long as you, you really need to redesign that sensing
amplifier.
And that was not, people have not found how to do it actually with less cost.
And that's why in DRAM we still do only two steps, like 0 and one.
But in PCM, actually easily we can do 4 steps, 8 steps or so.
And that's also a technology that we are also using in flash memory as well.
Like in today's flash memory, I think you've seen they call it QLC that essentially they store 4
bits in each flash set.
OK, So PCM has higher density and also PCM we don't need to refresh actually.
And that's why because PCM is considered as a resistive memory and usually memories that they are
based on charge.
Fundamentally they lose charge after some time and you need to refresh them.
But PCM is considered as a resistive memory and you essentially you don't need to refresh it and you
would keep the charge.
Another important thing about PCM is that they are non volatile, meaning that in DRAM when you if
you just turn off the electricity, then DRAM is going to lose the charge, right.
But PCM will retain the charge even without electricity.
So.
And that's another very important reason that PCM can be used as a persistent memory.
DRAM cannot be used as persistent memory and that's why you always need to back DRAM with your disk
when you want to have persistent data.
But PCM can provide persistency because they don't lose charge by cutting off the electricity.
Yeah and the manufacturing PCM is actually not very, you know, mature.
So I show that Intel, for example, has done it.
But for for them also they realise that the overhead of that is actually huge and at some point
didn't make sense to them to continue the line.
From the business perspective.
These memory, PCM and also some other emerging memory technologies, they have endurance problems
which essentially you cannot write, raise and write or hear only write after NN times.
So for example, in PCM, if you write 10 to the power, 8 to a cell, then the cell is going to be out
and you cannot write reliably or even write and read from that cell.
And that's the endurance problem, which in order to make your memory reliable, you need to deal with
that with those issues as well.
I should say that actually flash memory also has the same problem, but people are designing a system
around flash memory, the story stop system in order to, you know, solve this problem and also many
other problems that they have, OK.
And PCM has higher access energy, especially, right energy for PCM is much higher because of this
process that you need to change the of the phase of the measure.
OK, any question.
I mean, these are just quick overview of these technologies, but if you really want to learn about
them, we have some lectures that I'm going to point you from, from our advanced course that you can
check.
OK, I'm going to also distinguish between these memory from charge memory and resistor memory.
As I also mentioned, charge memory, essentially you write data by capturing some charge.
And this is actually similar in DRAM.
Flash memory is also the same.
The technique is a bit different, but essentially also in flash memory in each cell you capture
charge.
I'm not going to detail of that, but that's also based on charge.
And then when you want to read, you need to read data by detecting the voltage, like how much charge
you have it stored.
Whereas in resistive memory you write data by pulsing some current and read data by detecting the
resistive of that material.
So charge memory is unfortunately are fundamentally prone to this losing charge and that's why you
need to refresh them.
In DRAM you need to refresh every 10s of millisecond.
In flash memory, you don't.
You don't need to refresh them that frequently, but still you need to refresh once a while, like
once a week or twice a week in order to, you know, have your data available.
If you if you just store your data in a flash cool disk and don't access your flash memory for
several years, then you may not be able actually to, you know, get your data reliably.
But our s s DS today are actually doing that in at the storage controller.
OK, but resistive memory, they don't have this problem, but they also have some other problems that
in the end is a trade off design.
So there are, there are many actually different, let's say emerging memory technologies.
But these are some promising resistive memory technologies, PCM, which we have already discussed
about it a little bit that you inject current to change the material phase and then we determine
the resistance, resistance of the of that face.
There is also another technology SCT MRAM.
It's been, it's been torque memory MRAM, like, yeah, I forgot what was what does it stand for?
But yeah, anyway, it's say transfer torque.
Yeah, it's been transfer torque.
Thank you.
Which in inject current to change magnet priority.
So basically there is a.
Well that by injecting current you can change the polarity of that magnet and there is a reference
to that and you can check understand whether or not you restore zero or one by checking the the
polarity of that magnet.
So, and there is also another other memory technologies, memory store, which you essentially inject
current to change the atomic structure and resistance determined by atom distance, essentially.
So yeah, if we want to learn more about these, you can check our lectures.
And essentially there are pros and cons among these technologies.
And unfortunately, there is no single perfect technology that we can use everywhere in the whole
memory system that we have.
OK, yeah, these lectures you can check if you're interested.
I'm just flashing them.
But I just want to also mention that why is important to study emerging memory technologies.
So flash memory that's today actually seems very, let's say, obvious technology that we need to use.
Like we use S, S, DS.
We have a lot of flash memory also in our smartphones.
But this technology actually was a very doubtful technology for several decades.
And there were some, you know, persistent people and intelligent people that they really work hard
on it to make it possible.
And now we are seeing, you know, our system with flash memory, without flash memory.
For example, we should have like carry a smartphone with a large DRAM or some let's say HT DS, which
is not really interesting to have.
But flash memory actually provides this possibility that people can store reasonably high amount of
data in a in a lower capacity.
And so that actually caused some would actually cause revolution in the phone, mobile phone
technologies.
OK.
So in this paper actually, we discussed a lot about, you know, we characterize different errors and
how people mitigate them and how we can recover in flash memory base papers from 2017.
OK.
And I should say that actually flash memory, we, it's very actually has a lot of issues and it's
very interesting.
And in our SSD, we have SSD controller which is designed around flash memory to make sure that would
basically all these difficulties and problems of flash memory are not exposed to the, to the host
system.
So as a, as ACPO or the operating system, you, you really don't know, you don't need to deal with
difficulties of flash memory.
There is this interesting system designed around it, which would solve all these problems, but you
can check if you're interested.
OK.
And also we have some lectures in flash memory that's in our advanced course.
We also have a course as a bachelor course PNS, which this semester also, we have a version of it
SSD course that Rakesh is teaching that he's not here, I guess, but yeah, so you can check this.
We're going to also have this course next semester as well.
So if you're interested, you can follow that as well.
OK.
And there are also a lot of talks on on these different topics.
I will also mention that processing memory is another important thing.
So so we discuss about the problems of the memory.
So it's kind of, I'm concluding, you know, the, the part of the memory technology for, you know, the
section of this lecture.
But essentially we discuss about the problems of the DRAM and how memory DRAM is fundamental to our
system.
Like there are a lot of problems of DRAM.
And so the to solve these problems, one way would be look into some other technologies.
And that's why looking to emerging memory technology is important.
But another important way of solving this problem is actually also changing the paradigm or the
perspective of our design.
So we've seen that essentially we you actually there was a slide in the previous lecture that we
discussed about how costly to bring data from the main memory to the processor.
And so that's actually we want to minimise data movement in our system.
And a lot of this problem is actually coming from the fact the way that we are doing computation
following a fun human model that we bring data from the storage from the memory to the processor to
do computation and then we store back to the main memory.
So we are very much processor centric in this.
I would say actually kind of book now because it's actually very long.
We discussed how the changing the paradigm by doing more memory centric and doing computation in
memory or where data resides essentially would provide much higher performance and also energy
efficiency and sustainability.
So it's also very interesting to look into that way of designing systems because that would give us
much better perspective and how we can change the system as we go in future.
We also have some courses specificating for PIM processing memory in in our group.
If you're interested, you can check.
OK, so with that, I conclude the the first part of this lecture and now I want to get to memory
hierarchy.
But any question OK, I'm not seeing any hands.
So, so memory hierarchy in is actually something that we have in our all our system.
And I think by now you can actually guess why we need memory hierarchy.
So we have different we've essentially we want to get to the ideal memory, which is let's say 0
access latency.
But I would say, I would say that small or low memory access latency, but at the same time you
really want a huge memory and these two are actually conflicting.
There are also many other metrics or parameters that they're also conflicting.
And in order to work around it, people are designing memory hierarchy.
You've seen actually hierarchy before in this course as well.
When we discussing about register file, we have some registers in order to store some temporary
variable.
So we don't go to the to the main memory like for all these access, we try to have some registers
and try to capture some intermediate variables in those registers.
And so that's actually kind of a memory hierarchy that you know by now also you have register file
and then you have a main memory.
But in fact, actually memory hierarchy is much more, we have several layers levels of caches which
we're going to see much more in today's lecture.
So these are some, you know, the chips from different, you know, different systems.
And so here we have a core which has registered for L1 cache and also you have L2 cache and then you
have some DRAM interface and you have this DRAM S And as you can see that DRAM is actually kind of
dis disjoint.
It's separated from the processor chip.
And these caches are mostly actually SRAM because of the, you know, faster access latencies.
Yeah.
And this is also another example from Apple and it's also from Apple M1.
And in the past, actually processor like L2 was, was a separate chip from the processor chip.
But as the advancement in the real SI technology, people basically integrate L2 and now also L3 in
the processor chip to make, you know, provide much higher bandwidth caches and much higher also
higher density cache.
OK.
So yeah, these are some example from other different system, AMD Ryzen.
They also now doing this 3D level cache as well in AMD systems in I, I guess in Ryzen, actually in
Ryzen 7000 or so.
And after that, they have a 3D level of SRAM, which provides much higher capacity for caches.
OK, Yeah.
These are also some things about L1 and scratchpad which we're going to get back to that actually
later.
So I don't want to go into it now.
OK.
So the reason we are designing hierarchy actually is because of this that we cannot really get these
metrics together.
We cannot get any of them also.
But to work around it, we design Hierarchy.
So ideal memories requirement oppose each other, bigger is slow and faster is also more expensive
and higher bandwidth is also more expensive.
So when your memory is bigger it takes longer to determine the location and also from the.
So when you want to design A faster memory, even for one technology, you, you may you pay much more
like for a SLAM.
Actually there are different ways of designing a SLAM from which transistor we are using.
We have a high performance transistor, we have low power transistors and if you use high performance
transistor you're actually you know paying more for lower latency for DRAM, SSC and so on and so
forth.
So but even if, but by also from the perspective of memory technology, different technology actually
provides different latency and different cost as you've seen before also and from higher bandwidth
is also is more expensive because when you want to increase the bandwidth, you need to add banks,
you need to have more ports, more channels and higher frequency or faster technology and all of
them would actually contribute in higher in more cost in that memory.
So here are some numbers actually from the 2020 circa 2023 or so that essentially, you know, I don't
expect you to actually to.
Memorize any of them.
But just to give you some perspective, we actually have a yeah, we also have a table view.
So yeah.
So with different memory devices, RAM, you know the you can have a smallest Rams and that would
provide latency of sub sub nanosecond.
You can also have around KB or MB of SRAM that they provide some latency around like in order of
nanosecond.
And here also you can see the cost per MB.
So for SRAM actually the the cost is much higher compared to you know, other memories.
DRAM you can have capacity of gigabytes, latency is around 50 nanosecond or more or so.
And also the cost per is lower compared to SRAM PCMD, which is actually Intel obtained that is
actually longer access latency of that is longer compared to DRAM, but is less costly compared to
the data.
You can also use this technology for SSD, as I said that provides higher, you know gigabytes of
memory and also in order of TB.
But you can see that the latency now we are actually in territory of microseconds, so it can be 10
microseconds or so.
Flash memory provide much higher capacity, but they are also much slower, like 50 to 100
microseconds.
And hard disk are also much you can they can provide much higher capacity, but they are also much
slower.
So basically this table shows you that bigger is a slower and the cost is actually also decreasing
as we go to this technology.
So faster is also more expensive.
There's also this, you know, data from the energies perspective, which I'm not going into detail of
that.
But for that also you can see that we need to spend much higher energy when we want to get data from
these, you know, other like bigger memory technologies which they are far also further from us,
like getting data from the DRAM, you know, you need to consume much higher energy compared to SRAM.
And that's why by processing memory, we try to argue that basically it's not really it's not
beneficial, it's not good or efficient to move that data that much.
So if you if you, if your data actually storing SYSI in flash memory and you want to bring that data
to your SRAM and then to the processor, you need to consume a lot of energy, which is not really,
you know, efficient.
So it's better to do computation where data resides as much as possible.
OK.
And here is also the the slide from 2011.
So you can also check numbers are a bit different, but just for your perspective you can also check
it.
OK, so we want both fast and large memory, but we cannot achieve both with the single level of
memory.
And the idea is that we want to have multiple levels of storage that progressively they are coming
bigger and slower as the levels are farther from the processor and ensure most of the data the
processor needs is kept in the faster levels.
So if you can make sure that most of your data actually or ideally all of your data can be accessed
from the cache from that small memory which we have, then the processor is going to experience only
the access latency of that fast memory.
By the same time you have huge memory to back that small memory, which in the end provides, you
know, larger space for, for the programmer and also us.
So the memory system looks like something like that, that you have actually some caches, some levels
of caches which they are small and fast.
But then you also have main memory, there can be other memory, you know, the hierarchy, you can also
think of SSDSHDDS, tape and so on and so forth.
But essentially we have a hierarchy in the memory system.
So we want to basically we want to move what we want to use here to the fast and small memory, which
hopefully with the good locality of references, we're going to talk about different, you know,
aspects of locality.
But as much as hopefully we have locality in memory accesses, we can hopefully, you know, the access
the memory as fast as the small, you know, the small memory and also have as large as the, you
know, the big large, but a slow memory.
You're going to see that in order to make it effective, you actually need to, you know, add more
levels in the pipeline in sorry, in your memory hierarchy.
So it's not only one level of cache.
We're going to have different levels in the memory hierarchy.
And again, as we go down the hierarchy, we're going to get, you know, memory that they are larger,
but they're also slower and also less costly.
OK.
So, yeah, that's the fundamental trade of that.
We're going to see that essentially fast memory is small, large memory is slow, and we design memory
hierarchy for that, OK.
And you've seen register file as well.
So register file is also part of your memory hierarchy.
But that register file is backed by some levels of caches and then main memory, hard disk and so on
and so forth.
OK, in this slide also you see different levels of cache as an example and the capacity that they
provide.
So L1 cache provides capacity around 10s of KB and we want to access L1 cache around 1 nanosecond.
L2 is hundreds of KB and access latency around let's say 5 nanosecond and L3 is several MB, but the
access latency is around 10 nanosecond and main memory is several GB which is access latency of 100
nanoseconds.
And you can actually continue that by talking about s s, DS and St.
DS.
So these are some numbers from this also paper.
Nowadays numbers might be a little bit different, but overall you got the idea that, you know, we
have fast at the top level and slower at the bottom.
OK, so why this memory hierarchy works?
The reason is actually because locality principle that essentially in general, without talking about
the memory one's recent past is a very good predictor of the near future.
And we've seen that a lot actually, you know, in our also everyday life.
And I would also, you know, defining two different ways.
So locality can be temporal.
So if you just did something, it is very likely that you will do the same thing again soon.
Like, like if you are sorry, in our, in our lecture, actually in DDC lecture, there are some
students that they are attending almost all the lectures.
So if, if you're attending, there is really, you know, high chance that you're also attending
hopefully the next lectures.
And, and we've seen that actually a lot.
And there are, if you're not attending, you're, you're going to continue not attending as well.
So that's the kind of temporal locality that you can think of and or for example, if you're
listening now, there is a chance that you're going to continue listening.
If you're not listening now, there is a chance that you're not you're not listening very soon as
well.
So that's temporal locality.
Since you are here today, there is a good chance that you will be here again and again regularly.
We also have a special locality, which if you did something, it's very likely you will do something
similar or related in the space.
Meaning that every time I find you in this room, you are probably sitting close to the same people
and or in close by seats like, I don't know, you can think of maybe you have some, you know,
regions that you're sitting mostly in the lectures and that's kind of a special locality that you
can think of.
OK.
But we also have memory locality, which we're going to use actually in order to make this memory
hierarchy effective.
So a typical program has a lot of locality in memory references.
And first of all, typical programs are components of loops.
So you have a loop and you're going to, you know, iterate on that loop.
So like instructions that you have inside your loops, you're going to access them right iteratively.
So you're going to have temporal locality in those accesses.
And there are some references, some let's say for example, you have a contour and you want to
increment that contour, you know, so that contour, which is a memory address, a variable that you
store in memory, you have some locality for that which you're going to access that and increment
that again and again.
So that's the kind of a temporal locality that you can think of.
Also in terms of a special locality.
Most of we are we are operating a lot on arrays, OK.
And in arrays, actually memory references are, you know, close by or so think about SIMD also
lecture that we discuss about stride.
So memory accesses can be a stride of 1.
So you're going to have a special locality in your memory accesses.
OK, So that's the kind of special locality that we have in data access because we are working on
arrays.
But from the perspective of instructions also, if you think about MIPS for example, instructions are
usually the previous instruction plus 4, right?
So you always have this kind of a special locality in your accessing instructions.
Sometimes we don't have because of the branches, but overall instructions are continued.
So temporary program tends to reference the same memory location many times and all within a small
window of time and especially program.
Tends to tends to reference nearby memory location within a window of time, and we've seen that from
instruction memory references and references to arrays and vectors.
OK, so it's a good place to stop.
We will continue after the break, so let's get back at 3:15 when the ring bells when the bell rings.
OK, let's let's continue.
So we discuss about temporal and special locality and and essentially caching is, you know it's
designing based on this locality that we have.
So we design caching based on to exploit temporal locality.
So the idea is that we want to store recently access data in automatically managed fast memory.
So you automatically managed, meaning that this programmer transparent that we usually call as
cache.
There is also, you know, software managed of, you know, design for cache that people call it usually
scratch pad memory.
So when you when you talk about cache, we usually mean that it's actually hardware managed or
automatically managed.
And so essentially the anticipation here is that the same memory location will be accessed again
soon.
And here we are actually benefiting from temporal locality principle.
And this is actually what's also Maurice Wigs.
Wigs had in mind, if you know about him is the is the one that also designed this micro code micro
architecture, multi cycle micro architecture.
And so, so basically this is, you know the writing from from this paper that the use the uses
discuss of a fast core memory of say 32,000 words, which is quite a small compared to the you know,
the memory sizes that we have today.
So this 32,000 words as a slave to a slower core memory of say 1,000,000 words in such a way that in
practical cases the effective access time is nearer that of the fast memory than that of the slow
memory.
So essentially you know there is a small memory as cache which people have designed long time ago as
well.
Also we want to exploit the special locality so we store data in addresses adjacent to the recently
accessed one in automatically managed fast memory.
So essentially we logically divide memory into equal size blocks and we fetch to cache the access
block in its entirety.
So whenever, for example, the program has a memory access, which can be like byte, you know, you
want to fetch a byte or you want to fetch a word, you don't only bring that byte or word from the
memory to the cache.
You basically bring that word and also around that word.
You know, I said the whole block, which can be several words like 64 bytes.
And with that you can, you're trying to benefit from the special locality by saying that I, I
already accessed this byte.
So hope probably I'm going to access the neighboring bytes as well in near future.
So I'm bringing the whole cache block or the whole these equal size blocks to the to the cache in
order to, you know, access them fast in future.
And that's if you, if you, if you can benefit from them, that's a bingo.
Like it's great.
We can, you know, have this access in the cache.
So, and that's especially because the principle that nearby data in memory will be accessing in the
near future.
And we've seen that in accessing the instruction and also error traversal.
And this is also what in IBM36085 also implemented that they had 16 KB cache with 64 byte blocks.
Now it is also still block sizes around 64 is actually 64.
GPU might use longer cache blocks like 128 or so, but still the idea is the same.
So you bring that block in order to benefit from special locality.
So by temporal locality, you bring the memory access, the basic, the location that you want that you
access.
You're saying that near future I'm going to access that location as well.
So I'm going to bring that to the cache.
But for special locality, you're saying that I'm bringing that location and also around that
location because I'm in near future I'm going to access the neighboring bytes as well.
So I also like this bookshelf analogy that you can think of.
You might have, you have some books in your hand.
That's a computer architecture book.
And that's the book that you're taking your hand and you're operating on it, which you can think of
as your hand can be as a register, register file, OK.
And you also have a desk and that your desk, you can think of some like caches.
And so you put computer architecture books and some other books from your class that you need in
near future.
And then at some point your your desk gets full and then you put adjacent books in the shelf.
I mean, other books in the shelf and so on and so forth.
Also in the in the shelf, the way that you map your book is actually important, interesting.
Like those books that they are relating to the same topic, let's say computer architecture, you try
to put them.
I mean the, you know, the around same location in that shelf, because with that you can actually
fetch them much faster.
So that's also the way that we do try to, you know, exploit a special locality, you know, in our
daily routine as well, OK, So caching actually needs to be nicely integrated in the pipeline
design.
So the cache needs to be tightly integrated in the pipeline and ideally we want to access in one
cycle so that load dependent operation do not stop.
So remember about, you know, the pipeline design that we had before, we're saying that the memory
stage is going to take one cycle, OK.
So that can be handled actually if we consider we have some caches, OK.
But The thing is that that on one cycle then makes the cache actually quite a small.
So or in other way round, the processor needs to have high frequency.
And because if you want to have a cache which can be accessed with that higher frequency, you really
need to, you cannot make your cache large enough.
So you need large caches, but at the same time you really need to be able to access your cache fast.
So that's why people, you know, design cache hierarchy similarly with the same reason that we have a
level 1 cache which you can actually small and can be accessed quite fast, you know, in one or two
or four cycles.
And then you have some other levels of cache in order to provide much higher capacity for caches.
OK.
And that's cache hierarchy, which we're going to see that today as well.
Also a very quick note on manual versus automatic management.
So it can be the management of cache can be manual that programmer manages data movement across
levels.
So programmer decide where to put data.
And that's something that which is also called as scratch pad memory.
So that memory actually or cache if you if you will, needs to be actually part of the memory
addresses space such that you can decide where to put your memory at the software layer.
And it can be programmer or compiler that can, you know, help with that, but essentially is at some
point is going to be too painful for programmers on substantial programmes.
So it's actually has been used in processor that they have very specialised use or some specific
applications.
Like if you think about embedded processors, you have very specific applications that you're running
on that processor.
So you may not you may not need actually caches and you can actually handle everything on a scratch
pad.
Memory or GPU is actually NVIDIA call them shared memory.
But later on also they realise that relying only on the scratch pad memory or shared memory is not
good enough because of the program programmer issues.
And they also introduce L1 and shared memory which can be used alternatively or in combination and a
lot of accelerators also they are using scratch pad memory.
Also, managing cache can be automatic, which hardware manages data movement across levels completely
transparently to the programmer.
So that makes the programming life easier.
And now the average programming doesn't need to know about caches.
And here is also very interesting.
So as a programmer, you don't need to know about caches if you only care about writing a correct
program.
But if you really want to also write a fast program, then, OK, then you may need to know about
caches because then you the way that you map your data, the way you access your data, you may, you
know, just reorder your operations in order to make sure that you can maximise the hit rate, for
example, in L1 cache.
So then if you really about care about the speed of your program, you do need to care about caches,
the size of the cache.
But but if if you only care about the correctness of the program, you don't really need to do care
about it care about the caches.
OK, so here also some example that essentially in in some architectures we use caches and scratch
pad which is a software managed cache together.
So in GPU actually initially they have only scratch pad but later on as they want to run more
general purpose application in GPUs which they call it GPGPU general purpose GPUs.
They basically they realise that having only scratch pad is not enough and they also added L1 cache
and there is a shared memory capacity in this architecture in amper 2020 is actually 192 KB per
streaming multiprocessor.
And the programmer can decide how much of this space want to allocate to L1 cache and how much to
scratchpad memory or shared memory in other technologies also and other, you know, versions of GPU
like this one in Hopper 22,022.
They also have, you know, larger size.
So they keep this, you know, this flexibility that we can decide between L1 cache and scratcher
memory.
And at the same time they also make it larger because of the memory bottleneck problems.
OK, this is also a Cervus which you have seen that also in previous lectures.
And they also have a, you know, a huge on chip memory, 18 GB of on chip memory, which provide 9
petabyte per second.
And this is also considered as a scratch pad memory.
And you can, you know, program the the programming.
OK, I just want to also quickly give you some historical perspective.
This actually a magnetic drone memory, which was the the main memory of this, you know, of these
years, 1950s to 1960s and later on people designed.
So this is actually quite huge.
It's not.
So that's why computers in the past were also very huge for the memory perspective aspect.
And they designed this magnetic core memory which was if you look at into it actually it's very
much, you know, again, you can see this structure of array which the cell is different is magnetic,
but the structure of the array is very much similar to what we, you know, use today's in DRAM or
memory arrays in general.
So this core memory was the main memory of the year 1960s to 1970s.
And then there is a writing here which I can quickly actually read it.
So using a smaller cores and wires, the memory density of core slowly increased and by late 1960s a
density of about 32 kilobits per cubic per cubic foot was typical.
However, reaching this density required extremely careful manufacture and actually currently is also
the same.
When you want to increase density, you need to put a lot of effort in manufacturing.
And yeah, which was almost always carried out by hand in spite of repeated major efforts to automate
the process.
So yeah, there are also some writing about the cost.
And then essentially the introduction of the first semi inductor memory chips in the late 1916,
which is initially created static random access memory, SRAM, and later on DRAM, which has been
used in Intel 11-O3 in 1970.
They actually slowly, slowly replace the core memory.
And nowadays we have DRAM memory as the main memory of the system.
So that's before 1970 or so people have, you know, have other memories to use as a main memory.
OK, so this also the the paper that I talked about it previously.
And here also they call it as a slave memory, which basically this, you know, Maurice Wilkes say
that by a slave memory, I mean one which automatically accumulates to itself words that come from a
slower main memory and keeps them available for subsequent use without it being necessary for the
penalty of main memory access to be incurred.
Again, essentially benefiting from temporal locality, you know, in that slave memory.
OK.
And there are also some other papers from the past because caching actually has been an idea from
long time ago, which you can also check if you're interested.
And here is a picture from this paper that basically I'm going to show that in the cache structure
we have data store and tag store.
We're going to learn about both of them very soon.
But essentially data store is the location is the memory that you store.
You know, cache blocks or data itself, like the the exact data that you really you want to fetch,
you put them in your in data store.
But tag store actually provides some metadata that help you find your data essentially.
So when you want to understand which address is stored in your cache, you need to check your tag
store.
We're going to see that.
So tag store is kind of a metadata and data store is, you know, your actual data that you want to
operate on.
OK.
And this is a kind of a modern memory hierarchy that we have register file, L1L2L3 main memory and
also this.
So some of these levels are actually handled manually like register file is manual or compiler.
So compiler decides, you know how to map variables to registers and also compiler needs to you know,
put those instruction of register spinning.
When you don't have enough register, you need to for example use your stack.
You know, you write spin some registers to the memory to free some registers and then you use it
for, you know, for other use cases.
But other levels like L1L2L3 and these are actually automatic hardware cache management is most of
today's systems.
And then you have main memory, which is, you know, handled by the disk.
And this is actually based on the, your operating system is working on it.
So we're going to learn about it in a virtual memory lecture, hopefully in future.
I don't, I, I guess in the last lecture or the one lecture before the last, we're going to learn
about it, how we can manage this main memory and, and swap disk.
But this part is actually let's say controlled by software or I would say the operating system.
But these levels of cash or cash hierarchy is managed by hardware mostly in today's systems.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's a very good question.
We're going to get to that.
That's that needs a policy, which we call it right policy and we're going to get to that.
Very good.
Any other questions?
OK, so now let's see.
We want to analyse the performance of cache with some examples.
So a given memory hierarchy level, think about layer one, for example, L1 cache, which you can think
of level I has a intrinsic access time of TI.
So it's going to going to take some time when you want to access that memory either of L1 register
file L2L3.
So you have some access latency associated only with that memory layer.
You also have perceived access time, which is T capital I that is longer than TI, which actually
causing, you know, the the fact that if you cannot find your data in that memory layer, you need to
bring data from other layers, right?
And that's TI, which actually the the big TI.
So now you have this probability, you know the case that when you access your layer memory layer,
you might or might not find your data.
So a chance, which we call it hit rate HI that you hit.
And then you have going to have access time of TI.
And there is a chance that you miss in your that layer of memory or level of memory, sorry.
And access time is going to be TI plus TI plus one the other layers.
So you need to expand TI because you already accessed that level, you know, cache.
And then since you don't find it, you need to bring it from other levels.
So you basically add the latency, you know, perceived latency of accessing the the next level of the
memory.
So that's TI plus one.
And this hit rate plus miss rate should be 1, of course.
So now we can actually write this recursive function.
TI for each layer is going to be hit rate times TI which is the intrinsic access.
And then if you miss in that level, you need to already pay the, you know, the penalty of accessing
that level and also the perceived access time of the other the next level, which is TI plus one.
And if you work around this equation, you're going to get to TI equals to TI plus miss rate times TI
plus one.
OK, which makes sense, right?
So that's that's basically the the recursive function that you have here.
And the H hit rate and miss rate are defined to be the hit rate and miss rate of only the references
that miss at Li -1.
So essentially when you so when you say that, so at the at the layer one like L1 cache, you, you,
you see 100% percent of accesses, OK.
And if you're hit mist rate is for example 10%, then you're going to service 90% of accesses in L1
and then 10% of that 100% of requests going to get to other levels.
And for other levels, you define mistreat and hit rate again with respect to the amount of
references requests that they're going to get to.
So if you say that the level 2 heat trade, for example, is 50%, which means that you're going to
heat half of the requests that are going to filter that are going to pass L1, that they are not
filtered by L1.
So that's the definition of heat rate and mistreat if you want to have this equation correctly.
OK, now we have this recursive latency equation and the goal is that we want to achieve.
Desired T1, which is the access latency of L1 cache within allowed cost.
So basically we want to have this TI equals to, you know, intrinsic TI, which is a desirable moment.
So of course the ideally if miss rate is 0, you're going to get to that TI equals to T, the small I.
But the the moment that you have some misses, you're not going to get to that, but you want to
minimise the difference.
OK.
So we want to, in order to achieve that, you essentially have two trade off.
You can keep miss rate low.
So you want to reduce miss rate as much as possible.
And that is by increasing, you know, the capacity of lawyers and also by yeah, exactly by increasing
capacity.
But we should also be aware that increasing capacity would also increase the intrinsic latency.
So this actually very important, we can provide higher capacity and providing lower miss rate, but
that would also comes at the price of longer access latency for that level of cash.
So we should be careful about that and we can also lower miss rate by smarter cash management.
So we're going to see how we can design the cash and how we can make it smarter.
But essentially that would also need, you know, a lot of management to decide how to replace, how
what to not replace, what to not inserting the cash and also whether or not we want to prefetch in
the cash.
We're going to learn about all of these actually later today and also in other lectures.
Another way to, you know, achieve that is that we want to keep TT big TI plus one actually low.
So we want to make this one also low as much as possible.
So for that we have we need to have faster outer hierarchy levels and that's why we actually make a
cash hierarchy.
We have a deep cash hierarchy.
That's one of the reason to make this TI plus one, you know, as low as possible.
Yeah, introduce intermediate hierarchy device as a as a compromise.
OK, we're going to see an example actually and the size of the caches that we're going to assume is
actually coming from Intel Pentium 4.
We're going to consider 16 KB L1 cache and one MB L2 cache.
OK, so here is an example.
This is a processor Intel Intel Pentium 4 L1 data cache is 16 KB.
Access latency of that is 4 cycle.
Actually because of the you know the the because the frequency of the processor is actually 3.6
which if you have considered one nanosecond access latency for your cache you really need several
cycles to access that.
And L2 is 1 megabyte and it takes 18 cycles.
And main memory we are considering 1550 nanosecond which actually kind of idealise here or 180
cycles.
There are also some notice here that best case latency is not one.
So we cannot access L11 cycle.
So the best case is not one.
And also worst case access latency can be actually much more than 500.
And here we are actually simplifying the the the problem for for this example.
OK, so this is the essentially the the equation that we are looking at.
So assuming that miss rate of L1 cache is 0.1 and miss rate of L2 cache is 0.1, you can calculate T1
and T2.
So T1 actually is the is the most important latency for this case because that's the latency that
processor is going to see.
OK, T2 is going to be the latency for L2.
You know, when L2 needs to, you know, fill that's going to be the latency that we're going to see.
But L but at L1T1 is the one that trusts or cares much.
So when mistake is 0.1, meaning that 90% of the requests are going to hit in L1 cache.
So for 90% of the requests we're going to see only four cycle and for 10% of request we're going to
access the other levels of memory.
So out of this 10%, 90% is going to hit in L2 and the rest is going to we need to access the main
memory.
So that's the meaning of this different miss rate that we're going to see.
And with that you can calculate that.
Unfortunately, we don't have time to calculate today, but you can also do it easily.
If we consider that miss rate is actually 0.01, meaning that hit rate is 99% and also the miss rate
of the L2 is also 0.01, then the T1 is going to be 4.2.
OK.
Which yeah, which is actually really, really good, so.
Here actually I want to show a trade off with these two numbers.
So one way would be like the miss rate of I can relax you know the because getting 99% hit rate in
L1 is not that easy.
So one way would be basically we relax the miss rate of L1 to have like 95% hit rate.
And then if we have a very good L2 that can provide 99% hit rate, then we're going to have a latency
of five cycle cycles, which is relatively close to 4.
But another way is that if you have a very good L1 which provide 99% hit rate, then actually at L2
we can actually have a much relaxed L2 design.
So that gives you a trade off.
If I do a really good job at L1, I can be actually relaxed at L2L3 and other layers.
So having AL 2 with hit rate of 50% again going to give us the the same number of overall the same
number as the previous example.
So that's a trade off that people try, you know how much they're going to pay effort on making L1
better and how much they're going to pay effort to make other levels better.
Because in the end the cost is limited and we want to essentially we want to design intelligently
considering the the cost that we have.
This does not, no.
But you have techniques to hide memory latencies.
You have techniques in your in your processor to hide memory access latencies as much as possible.
Like we have ILP, we have TLP and with those actually you that hopefully you can actually tolerate
that 1% that you are missing in L1.
OK.
But I agree.
I mean, yes, at some point you we need to if you care about for example the you know, the tail
latency, there might be some cases that you're going to have very long latency and that can you
know cost some quality of service for example for us.
But that's yeah, that can be a problem.
But in general purpose application, I would say that that's not a problem, Yes.
OK, so I'm going to go into detail, a bit more detail of how we design caches and we see some
operations.
So cache essentially any structure that memorized use or produce data to avoid repeating the long
latency operations required to reproduce and fetch the data from scratch.
So that's the cache.
And actually the idea has been used not only in, you know, in computer architecture and processor,
but also in other domains like web cache for example, that you know your browser actually is
caching a lot of data while you are browsing, you know, pages.
So most commonly in the processor design contest and automatically manage memory structure basically
memorising fastest RAM, the most frequently or recently accessed DRAM memory locations to avoid
repeatedly paying for the DRAM access latency.
So we've seen already all of this, this is a conceptual picture of a cache that essentially in your
cache you're storing cache block.
The reason we have cache block is actually to benefit from a special locality.
And then in each of your associated.
So each of your cache block is actually have 64 byte of data assuming your block is 64 byte.
And also you need to have some some tag which is a metadata information about the cache block like
the address or part of the address and some other metadata that we're going to see.
So that's what we store in the cache.
So now the question is that the logical organization of a cache, we need to ask this question how to
map chunks of the main memory addresses space to blocks in the cache.
So we know that we need to divide the memory addresses space or physical addresses space into
chunks.
So how are we going to map these chunks into the cache?
That's the question that we want to answer.
So essentially which location in cache can a given main memory chunk be placing?
And with that we can have a different, you know, strategy.
One way would be fully associative that especially like essentially each chunk can be placed in any
location in the cache.
So any each chunk can be basically.
Mapped to any location your in your cache.
So that's fully associated.
Another strategy could be direct mapped, which essentially by your chunk that has a has an address
and you basically use that address by some hashing.
And then it say that OK, I'm going to that address with that hashing point to some location specific
location your cache.
So that chunk can be is going to be placed only in one option one location in the in the cache and
that's direct mapped.
And another way would be something between these two, right.
So you can have you can divide your cache into some sets.
So each chunk will be mapped to one specific set using similar strategy of direct mapped.
But in that set you you're actually storing in a fully associative cache.
So in each set you are fully associative, but among sets you're direct mapped.
OK.
And that's the that's the way people design set associative cash.
We're going to also see that.
So these are three strategies that we're going to look into details of that.
But any question from this high level?
OK, so one of the terminology here is block, like cash block or line.
Also people call it cash line.
That's the unit of a storage in the cache.
And memory is logically divided into blocks that map to potential local location in the cache on a
reference.
It can be so hit if in cache use cache data instead of accessing memory.
So if if you access your cache and you have a you encounter a hit, then basically use your data and
you don't access other memory layers if it's miss, if not in the cache, then you need to bring
block into the cache and that's would cause some plenty.
And when you do that you may have to evict some other block.
Essentially the reason is that like for example, direct mapped, if the another cache block that
you're bringing to your cache is is also mapped to the same cache block, then essentially you need
to evict the cache block that is already stored and store the new one.
And also instead associated, you may not have free, you know, you in your sets, you may not have
free locations.
So you need to, you know, replace something.
OK, so there are some important cache design decisions which we're going to see that actually most
some of them today, some of them in the later lecture that one of them is placement where and how
to place and find the block in the cache.
So that's more or less, you know the question about direct map set associative or fully associative.
Another problem is replacement what data to remove to make room in cache when the when your set is
full or even the whole cache is full in fully associative cache.
So where what do you want to how do you make room for the new, you know for the new data?
Also granularity of management.
Are we operating on large or small blocks or even we have sub blocks?
We're going to see that you can have a cash flow, you can divide it to some sub blocks and which has
been using some caches called sector cache for example.
And then you can operate on smaller sub blocks.
We're going to see that later.
And how you manage with rights, which one of your colleague asked which is right policy?
What do we do about rights?
And are we also treating instructions and data separately?
Like do we have separate instruction cache and data cache or the others, you know, managed to get
OK.
So that's again cache abstraction and metrics.
So essentially for your address, you have A tag store, which we use to see to basically, you know,
do some bookkeeping for us.
And also we use tag store to to answer this question that is the address in in the cache or not.
So basically by checking tag store, we can decide whether or not it's hit or miss, OK?
And if it's heat, then we can fetch the data from the data store.
So that's data store that we actually store the date, OK.
And these are the terminology that you are already seeing like cache heat rate is number of heats
divided by total accesses or number of heats plus number of misses and average memory access time.
Aim at it's going to be hit rate times hit latency plus miss rate times miss latency.
So this miss latency is going to be that, you know, the latency that you're observing from the
other, you know, from the immediate next level and hit latency is going to be the access latency of
that specific, you know, level that you're accessing.
OK.
There is also a site here that we're going to get to that hopefully later today which we're going to
get to that.
But basically we are want to answer this question is reducing a mat always beneficial for
performance?
We're going to get to that.
But you can start thinking about this question from now.
That's it.
OK.
So let's start with the basic design.
So main memory is logically divided into blocks and cache can house only a limited number of blocks.
So each block address maps to potential location, the cache determined by the index bits of the
address.
So we're going to start with the, you know, this kind of a design for direct maps that essentially
this is your 8 bit address.
You have some bits, so you use different bits in your address for different use cases.
Like for example, if you're in your cache, you have 8 locations that you can store your data.
You're going to, you need 3 bits in order to, you know, map find your location in that cache.
Kind of a trick map actually.
So you use three bits for that because 2 to the power 3 is 8.
And then in your caches you store blocks and each block can be in this example can be like 8 bytes.
So your block is 8 in this example.
So that's why you store for example 3 bits for that.
That's the offset in your cache block.
And you need to store the rest of the address as tag in your tag array and that will be used as a
comparison to make sure that we are heat or not.
So when we want to access cache, we index into the tag and data store with index bits in the address
and then we check valid bit in the tag store.
So we can associate one bit as a valid bit in each for each block.
Just to say that is this block that you're checking is empty or not.
OK, so if it's valid, then you're checking something you know valid and then you can see if it's hit
or not.
And we compare tag bits in address with the store tag in tag store.
And if the store tag is valid and matches the tag of the block, then we have cache hit.
OK, let's start with direct map.
And we're going to see so direct map a given main memory block can be placed in only one possible
location in the cache.
And in our toy example, we're going to consider a memory which is 256 byte.
And so our cache also is 64 byte and our blocks is 8 bytes.
OK.
So since we have 256 bytes in total and our blocks is 8 bytes then we we can store essentially in
our memory.
We have 32 blocks in memory but our cache actually store only eight blocks in this example.
So direct map is saying that the block can go to only one location.
So we have tag store and data store.
Data store is 8 locations and for tag store as well.
In tag store you have valid bit and tag.
So whenever you provide an address which is 8 bit.
You need some bits in order to point to your tag store and data store.
Since we have 8 locations, we need 3 bits to index.
You know, the data store and tag store and we also, since our blocks is is 8 bytes, we need also 3
bits in order to, you know, as offset which bytes are we locate are we accessing in that block.
So that's why we also need to use three bits of the address as a offset for that block and the rest
is going to be two bit as A tag.
So each memory address, you essentially you store the tag in your tag store.
And yeah, you store the tag.
And then you also need to set the valid bit.
When you have another access, you just you know, the tag of your address, the the two most
significant bits, you access the tag store with the index bit.
There is A tag store in your tag store and check the tag with your tag.
If, if these two are equal, then that's the hit.
If also a valid.
So if valid and also this tag and these two, this tag is equal, then it's a hit.
And then you can essentially fetch your data.
And here also we have a multiplexer which we're going to use, see which byte in that block we're
going to use.
So that's an offset.
Makes sense.
So that's direct map, which is actually pretty easy to understand.
OK, so The thing is that here blocks with the same index content for the same cache.
Location So in direct map all blocks that they have index of 000, they're going to be mapped to the
same location and which means that they're going to contend.
So some of them are going to, you know, kick out the previous one.
So for example, if you're accessing so previously initially you access block 0, this full zero and
then you put into the cache.
Later on you have this, you access block 01000, so this one also has the same index as the previous
one.
So you're going to access your cache and it's not a hit because your tag is different.
This one is 00 and this one is 01, so these are not the same.
I should also say that in this memory I'm showing the address for the block.
I'm kind of ignoring the three bits for the opposite.
So since they are not the same, you're that's a miss and you need to store this block.
OK.
So when you want to store this block, there is no other location.
You need to store it here, OK, in direct mapped.
So you need to kick out the block 0 that you had here to make room for the next block.
And that's a direct map problem that essentially you're going to have a lot of conflict.
We call it conflict.
Conflict misses question.
OK.
OK, Yeah.
So in direct map cache, two blocks in memory that map to the same index in the cache cannot be
present in the cache at the same time, one index, one entry and can lead to 0% hit rate if more
than one block access in an interleaved manner, map to the same index.
Like for example, you have these two block A&B and they are mapping to the same index.
If you're basically accessing A/B, A/B, A/B, A/B, you're going to have always conflict in your
direct map cache and your hit rate is going to be 0 essentially.
So for that people provide, you know, comes with this idea of set associativity that basically we
enable blocks with the same index to map to basically more than one location.
So we can have instead of 1 location, we can store in let's say 2, you know, locations or we can
store in eight or four locations.
OK, so this is our tag store and data store.
So in in set associative cache, you have two locations in this is actually I'm showing two ways set
associative cache.
So since your cache capacity is fixed, now you are you have less number of sets.
You don't have eight in the in the direct map we had eight locations vertically but now we have 4
sets.
But each set has two locations.
So you need to restore tag for both of them and when you want to check the heat you need to check
the tag of both locations.
So based on your address you are using two bits as an index because now you have only four sets.
Then you access your tag store for that and then you read these two valid bits and tags.
You also have A tag of your address which is 3 bits and you need to compare with your tag.
If either one of them is is heat, then they're going to be heat and you can get your data out from
data store and it's going to again your data store.
You also have two locations.
So this tells you which way in your set associative cache you are heating and you're getting data
out.
So this two way set associated cache question makes sense.
OK, yeah.
So with this idea, now you have you can accommodate conflicts better because you have fewer conflict
misses.
Now you have two locations, but if you need more, you need, for example, you can think of, OK, I'm
going to have four ways set associative.
But now I have 4 locations in my tag store in each row.
And then I'm going to also have only two sets.
And whenever you want to check the heat, you need to compare 4 tags essentially to see if it's heat
or miss.
And your data store also you need to Multiplex out four locations essentially.
So that's four set, four ways set associative cache.
So here if you think about the address, since you have only two sets, you're going to have only one
bit as an index because you only need to specify one among two sets.
And your tag is going to be 4 bits because, I mean, the rest of address is going to be used as A
tag.
So your tag array is actually becoming larger.
OK, just let me.
Yeah.
And full associativity, you're going to have actually the whole only one set and everything is going
to be used as a way.
So in this example, eight way set associative is going to be fully associative.
And whenever you see the heat, you need to check all these locations.
So we need to compare all a tax and that's fully associativity, which is the, you know, the extreme
case of designing this cash.
OK.
So I think it's a good place to stop.
Next week we're going to continue, you know, regarding this trade off between for the associativity
and the problems and challenges that it provides.
Have a nice weekend and I see you next week.
Thank you.